okay hello and welcome to another
episode it's been a while since I've
done a face to camera introduction and
it's still the truth I was always
shitted them always fucking hated them
and so actually this time I'm going to
read something out from what I already
have now I'm doing the intro to the
intro and well please bear with me and
there were some things I wanted to say
for grounding this conversation that I
would just take too long to say if I
didn't write them down first
joining me for this dialogue is Greg and
Rica's an award-winning professor of
graduate psychology at James Madison
University a man with a rare combination
of deep expertise and a breadth of
integrative perspective to match this is
an exciting conversation I think and my
sense after only coming to knowledge of
Greg's work a matter of weeks ago is
that this is someone who will have a
deep impact on the future of the science
of psychology or die trying' there's
energy and insight here that will be
very worthwhile for some of you to
investigate and track further but before
we get to our conversation I'm going to
say a few things that feed into each
other as I reflect on the library of
content this podcast features now hasn't
at all been about providing a 101
overview or introduction to someone's
thinking and this has created dissonance
at times when I speak to someone I seek
to arrive as quickly and as
appropriately as possible to a shared
relationship with possibility okay well
perhaps we can think about it better
like this the movements of understanding
or the practice of biological
transformation and the core of this
project if it flows and if it is most
effective arrives at the most
significant adjacent possible available
to mutual understanding co-creating
creating together in relationship this
is not so easy there are many obstacles
social cognitive normative logistical
game theoretic trust and vulnerability
and time and credibility thing you name
it now this is also a podcast so when I
sit down to record with someone that is
in mind and I do care about creating
things that are deeply helpful and to
take responsibility for my part in the
content Commons and so I do aspire to
create an art form that serves both the
ends of generativity and the necessary
sense of engagement and context that
properly serves you the listener
especially as this project continues to
and will expand its invitations to
participate in the emergent conversation
you can follow the links to check that
out to put it a slightly different way
and to foreground the theory and dynamic
I believe will become more clear
over the coming years and decades this
art form here aspired to will come to be
seen as a practice somewhat akin to an
emergent archetype of collective
realization so now back to Greg I'm
going to give a short introduction to
Greg's thinking not to articulate his
theory and not to speak for him but to
set the scene for some background
context to help you make sense of a
conversation that follows as far as I
can tell Greg Enrique seems to be here
to wake the world of psychology up again
to the importance of the very what that
the science of psychology seeks to
understand a man it's funny how the what
in things gets lost the what to care
about hey as I think about it it's quite
machine like this way we confuse
ourselves a machine consists of the
scripted processes it runs its method
without understanding of a more
essential nature of reality within which
or upon which it's processes operate the
machine might have functions or
imperatives whether it's a carry out
intended tasks with precision or
effectively generate paperclips but it's
missing something vital someone might
make the same case for human beings of
course doomed to ultimate ignorant as to
what we participate in I don't think we
all conceive our limitations in just
that way it's rather that we've placed
dead limitations on what the what could
be and more importantly stifled our
capacity to be in relationship with the
ongoing realization of that what I think
we've rather forgotten what maybe was
once known like the wisp of a dream the
deep quest of knowing ourselves each
other
and the world in favor of knowledge
about how to optimize for games we play
within it this bloody issue of survival
and fear and attachment we can weep for
that but not all the time it's a thesis
of this project that we need to
reimagine the games themselves the maps
themselves not for the maps or the games
themselves
but for the vitality and wonder to be
realized in the process of the game
making the map making the lovemaking but
we'll leave this as gesture now the
problem of psychology that Greg takes
his work to attempt to resolve is this
if you take a 101 site course you will
likely learn that psychology is the
science of behavior and mental processes
but the problem is that psychology has
sought to adhere to the methods of
science without an adequate unified
sense of what the reference behavior and
mental processes really mean and really
are there are many approaches within
psychology not defined the terms in
different ways but they are often in
conflict so it goes which amounts to
increasing fragmentation theoretically
and clinically so Greg's work is a
response to this problem by way of what
he terms the unified theory part of
which is the tree of knowledge system
which offers a map of cosmic evolution
as an unfolding wave of behavioral
complexity
he wants to coherently define behavior
and mental processes in a system of
descriptive metaphysics a map that not
only makes sense of the history of our
reality but one that also nods to the
conditions and dynamics which may
precede a radical phase transition or
emergence of a novel dimension of
complexity that may be just around the
corner I really enjoyed this dialogue
thank you for being here
I hope you get lots from it if you would
like to participate in conversations you
can go and follow the links in the
description there are conversations
happening all the time to the extent I
put out conversations these days without
offering those invitations I think it's
an error and not what it could be and
not part all timidly of the
philosophical art that must be created
in our time
okay
thank you for being here for the journey
that we're in it together let's go
so Greg I have just encountered your
work and I am aware it's very broad in
scope and that makes framing a
conversation that might introduce some
of your work and some of your ideas and
who you are
a bit challenging and it gives me an
opportunity to open things in a way that
I personally am most interested to open
and and perhaps that is with the most
abroad of questions so when you close
your eyes and perhaps not not you know
now we're in the last few seconds but
when you find yourself closing your eyes
and you are attending to just what the
hell is going on and perhaps not in a
way that's too confrontational like what
the hell is going on here you know
necessarily chaotic but just you
encounter ring that presence like it's a
familiarity and you exist and we exist
and here we are yes how have you begun
to make sense of the phenomenon of life
great that's a wonderful entry question
because what the hell is going on is a
great way of describing my logos in to
phenomenology as you well you know the
what the hell is going on right now is
particularly poignant of course with the
context of the virus and the world
experience of change and despair and
hope so I've been ever since you know
the shutdown and through March I've been
experiencing a lot of what the hell is
going on in terms of the global Kairos
of the moment
and that speaks to me in the deep ways
of both crisis and opportunity as in
terms of I see what is going on as a
crisis of our modern global experience I
also see in us at opportunity and I also
feel very much woven into the fabric of
it quite frankly I feel very connected
to it and simultaneously hopeful and
despairing in relation it's an
interesting tension to Zakarian
yeah this
relationship between hope and despair so
perhaps you find yourself at least in
part sort of in within this crisis
perhaps because of your work and
practice as a psychologist and clinical
psychologist but I also know you have a
deep interest in metaphysics and so in
what ways do those features of how you
show up in the world sort of help
articulate for our listeners how you
framed yourself now sure
so one is if I just put it in sort of
direct terms from for me one is the
relational phenomenological world as a
clinician I sort of have an intuitive
and have cultivated the an empathetic
experience where I connect to people I
mean that's what you need to do as a
clinician connect with the affective
phenomenological core of people and I'm
experiencing this globally then you know
in terms of the amount of suffering that
the wave of the medical crisis is
followed by the economic crisis followed
by the chaos and the uncertainty about
what the transition will be it impacts
me basically so you know it's a I don't
do I have a small clinical practice but
I you know go supervise and talk with a
lot of clinicians I know that there are
a lot of in a more raw and immediate
sense I know a lot of clinicians who are
on the front lines as it were of of at
least the mental health crisis and their
own experiences of 25 30 35 hours a week
on zoom listening to a person one person
after another who's just feeling trapped
her unbelievably anxious or dealing with
an entire medical crisis you know of a
family and so I'm fairly close to some
of them
stories and and my clinical side you
know I would stop being a clinician if I
stopped feeling that hmm so so that's
that's that's real
I you know I also you know know what's
good for me is to attend to that but
also recognize my local situations
remarkably safe and content relative to
the number amount of suffering that
other people are dealing with and it's
also important for you not to get lost
in that suffering so that I make my own
perspective and own local garden has it
worries fair number of garden metaphors
tend to my garden have a growth first
because I have a fortunate capacity to
not be in the wake and the immediate
destructive wake of systemic changes
that are unfolding hmm so that's you
know might the clinician in me is what's
what is the imagined person across from
the road and as a clinician you deal
with somebody who suffer most always
yeah I work by the temperatures so in
four five years four years when I was at
the University of Pennsylvania that's
all I work with so I have a and so where
do I so personality disorders depression
suicide that's my area of expertise and
needless to say that's mm-hmm
don't mean you know pretty heartfelt
trauma and tragedy on the flip side of
it when I think metaphysics I actually
think more I'm in my more hopeful
unified theory space need if we get the
Kairos of the moment right and you know
people like yourself and John verb a key
and other visionaries start to get
networked together and a collective
intelligence and we don't get brutalized
completely globally by a depression or a
series of events that knocks our global
system on its ass and we're actually but
enough to jolt us to wake us up to the
next 20 years
where
we made cumulative change in the right
way because we understand the actual
situation that we're in and we build the
right what I would call the destroy
descriptive metaphysical systemic
language that enables us to effectively
talk about what we are and what we're
doing and what we can do and that's my
that's my hope and I see a lot see a lot
of awakening collective intelligence in
the right direction and if that we can
make the transition from you know the
blue church I heard your jordan hall
discussion the the old institutions and
their old metaphysical commitment
inadequate metaphysical commitments if
we can make the right transition I get
very very hopeful of the kind of world
we might create yeah that's beautiful
great mm-hmm so in this hopeful look
towards some state of affairs where we
have increasing connectivity and
capacity for collaboration between those
who would truly be open to collaboration
in such a way that well beginning to
define it or articulate it from the
perspective of metaphysics or at least
what questions with elegance is not so
simple but something like how can we you
know Nora Bateson wrote a really
beautiful line in a recent essay and an
articulation of vitality as
relationships that build life that build
relationships that build relationships
those relationships I probably snuck in
an extra relationships there of course
we want we want the echo don't yeah
yeah so it's this yeah I would I would
just say so for me right there's the
core of our socio-emotional soul is the
need for what I call
value this is the experience of being
known and valued by important others so
we seek to be known and valued in just
the right way that's what that's what
our childhood heart wants our parents to
look at us and delight in us as they
protect us our lover to desire us it's
the process by which we're known and
valued by important others and really we
want to create a relational society that
we can mutually maximize with
authenticity and integrity and so you
know an interesting question might be
what are the wisdoms what what are key
things we should be aware of in this
hopeful movement towards establishing
the kind of network relationships which
can be appropriately open and in touch
with the life-giving ecology around us
both cultural and in nature and not just
opens up to so much complexity and but
there you go well right that's a
wonderful framing the complexity of the
problem and it is how do we align our
natures with each other the
technological and environmental
situations we find ourselves in a way
that Orient's is toward the good with
the good being grounded I think in the
relational value frame in many ways it's
a more complicated question but that's
the central point and I think that's a
point that the modernist version of
reality meaning the Enlightenment modern
science Liberal Democratic modern view
misses it's hyper individualistic and
hyper self interested in what it frames
our metaphysics of our nature to be and
that's Zach Stein as you
familiar we talked on the emerg pack us
about the metaphysics of love and having
we need to have a particular language
system that helps us understand exactly
what that is
that's not oxytocin chemicals bouncing
in our nervous system that's a
materialistic flat land disaster view
and a completely erroneous shoe so so
there are there's lots of I have lots to
say about that question some of which
would go into getting the right
metaphysics some of which would go into
getting the right ecology of practices
to use John for a keister to get the
right diet logos for us so that we can
connect horizontally with each other and
vertically from my head into my heart
into my body and create a harmonizing
synergy that allows us be known and
valued and and work together in solving
the actual problems that we need to be
confronted and directed at yeah I'd be
interested in getting your response to a
way of speaking about the dialogical
process that I seem to resonate with a
lot at the moment is how I at least
introduce some conversations I have
relate to them myself and that is
certain kind of dialogical conversation
which enables a movement of
understanding I'd be interested in well
so a movement there is some kind of well
just briefly a nod to the process yule
nature of our interdependence and the
seeming cycles of different states of
awareness different kinds of knowing but
also almost in almost in variability of
our forgetting there's somewhat of an
open question there as to what may be
possible
at the very edges of awareness in terms
of the continuity that's enabled I do
think there's something to be said for
striving for a continuity of awareness
that that that's important but we seem
to forget a and perhaps the forgetting
is is necessary for the remembering and
then there's this question of
understanding which itself from some
angles seems to shift but nevertheless
we can participate in it and
nevertheless with each other we can be
grounded in something valuable even as
that ground itself might move from
certain perspectives so I'd be
interested in just your take on how a
movement of understanding what that
triggers in your in your in your mind in
your body brilliant yeah and so a couple
of things captured there that I can riff
off for a bit so one of the things the
continuity of experience and also the
fading of experience captured me as we
ride the wave of our conscious
experience and then file away or
episodic memories but lose so much of it
right in relation and what is that
continuity and when do we feel like that
continuity is coalescing and building
and accumulative sense of understanding
and what I'm captured by there is the
idea that we're sort of on this when
we're looking to understand to use the
Jordan Peterson frame it's on me
the edge of the unknown we we explore
into that which we can't see we're
familiar with our home base and now we
want to find the edge of that and we are
looking to see what's relevant in this
new at the same time we're dancing and
moving and trying to participate in a
way that may or may not make sense when
we experience understanding there's some
of alignment and at least one of our
knowing systems to use John berbay these
four p's so we are either we even have a
perceptual Gestalt that allows our
perspectival going to see or we get a
propositional understanding that allows
us to unfreeze our belief and rearrange
them move for us to accommodation and
then grow into assimilation
propositional E or we experience that
participatory dance you know like a jazz
session between people and then we feel
known in relation R in our intuitive
inner subjectivities like hey I don't I
don't Tim I haven't met you very long
but man I kind of resonate and
experience that so so a lot of things
come up for me when we start to think
about understanding and knowing and
continuity and and I am seeking
understanding in many ways I'll often
say that wisdom and understanding or two
unbelievably foundational words for me
so it is the fundamental that more than
knowing it's the fundamental experience
of understanding which is broader its
knowings more propositional
understanding or participatory and
perspective all and grounded in body
yeah particularly important when we come
into touch with other people who well
might recoil from our touch necessarily
physically but let's say whether
energetically or proposition me
psychologically it does seem to be the
case that the continued fraction of
society is a possible future at least in
a short term which could have quite
drastic and negative consequences and
indeed already is to some degree and
then into some degree you know maybe
it's appropriate to fractionate if if
there's something dead about the there
the large you know collective
active block but navigating difference
opening into a shared space of
communication that is one that enables
at least some kind of reciprocity um
that is a level more reciprocal than
than violence you know what I'm trying
to say absolutely what do we have to
what do we have to be aware of what can
we be aware of to help enter into these
movements then how do we invite I like
to think how do we invite this is
something I'm so interested in how do we
invite participation in movements of
understanding right yeah and your
reflection on that's really key because
the framing of that to invite people in
is absolutely central if you don't have
sort of the preordained frame upon which
the arena that people are entering in
then good luck you know and
unfortunately many of our pre existing
institutional frames are essentially
designed to do almost the opposite they
are designed to commit you to a
particular institution you know
certainly in the United States our
socio-political framing is designed to
commit you to one side of the team that
is designed not to understand and to
design to compete with the other I mean
that is what that is what you know
article polarizer is so dramatic that
it's very even hard to find a particular
issue that doesn't that if you enter it
all in any kind of political discussion
immediately is polarized by you know you
you are then going to be attacked by the
other side and then you have to decide
whether to defend yourself okay and the
position is not about understanding but
about a primitive game a influenced
Machiavellian influence dynamic that is
designed to try to wrest power and
attention and resources away from some
other group and justify the short-term
gain of your own group and that is that
kind of mentality that kind of
interaction that
processes those it's too prevalent and
is scarily prevalent certainly in my
country's leadership so so I just use
that as an example about what how
frequently it is that you don't have
that and how dangerous it is and if you
try to enter into a game beat mindset
with people playing game a good luck
mm-hmm so what does that mean it means
we need to create a metacognitive space
of awareness of the rules of this
particular kind of language and
relational game that we are playing and
and it's a game of you know good faith
to use starters frame of reference it's
like okay I'm gonna commit to certain
higher values and I'm gonna commit to
particular kinds of ways of relating and
and ways of progressing that enable
constructive dialogue O's you don't
necessarily need to use those terms you
can just say hey I want to try to
understand you I want to understand what
your needs and values are I want to
share what my needs and values are and
let's see if we can understand each
other if we have problems let's see if
we can find solutions and I'm not going
to use violence or hostility or
character degradation in that process no
I'm gonna use you know and that's not
saying well always agree or won't
disagree sharply but it's to say that
we're engaged in a particular kind of
process that has rules and values that
they understand and commit to and those
provide the the guardrail cess of work
at least offer a guardrail free yeah
this this um the question of framing the
frame that is the thing to be taken
space in when we invite it's the
direction of the invitation or the kind
of it's what's brought along through the
invitation this is this really gets to
the core of a deep area of interest for
me and I think
I think maybe I thought maybe I think it
is on on the frontier of
how to make generative steps forward in
this space because when we talk about
frame making and inviting people into
frames we we have to have a certain
amount of self knowledge of just what
what actual frames we are bringing to
bear and we know of course we are
complex organisms and there's part of me
that have to frame that we're gonna
speak to each other for a couple hours
here there's it's part of me that's
gonna be hungry in four hours
certainly in 10 hours if we're still
talking by then I'd be like great mate
this is not what I sow and of course
it's and of course it's much more
threatening than all of that you know we
have this machinery in us we have this
capacity in us to be very moved by the
frames of others and of course the lens
of ideology the lens of various ways of
making sense are inform our
understanding of ourselves and the world
and so when we talk about rules we might
talk about the kind of education that
might be required in the ecology to have
people gain some sort of understanding
of these rules and then I think well
before that before that how can I
something I am interested in is how do I
and to communicate this to others how to
hold oneself how to come into a kind of
awareness of oneself and be in relation
to something greater than oneself a kind
of an ongoing process of frame making
that holds the dignity of human beings
in in critical esteem that they that
they are part of that process that there
is no frame for me if in some sense and
the invitation is not at least in
principle extended to all now that is a
crazy thing to say and I don't mean to
say it flippantly because there's so
much it's really
I think that well actually because I
felt like there's a lot of residents
with us I actually speak that language
quite deeply so I was just nodding along
with everything you were saying mm-hmm
so so to crystallize a question then
might be something like how how do we so
I almost don't want to even frame it the
very act of doing this is is something
I'm I'm I'm wary of part of me was
driven to to ask how can we come to an
understanding within or the kinds of
psychic technologies that might lend us
an understanding afford us the
transformation of our own understanding
of ourselves such that we can extend
invitations in more integrity but by the
same token there's something about
realizing that frame in dialogical
relationship with others that needs to
kin kick in very quickly because it's
not me just going off and being isolated
right and a whole bunch of stuff and
coming out and saying here play my game
it's so how do we so so well-kept yeah
so anyway this is definitely a lot this
is front and center to some of the stuff
that I'm working on and I can tell
you've been working on it also and you
know so here here's here's what I offer
and then and I offer it in the spirit of
what I call integrative plurals okay
integrated means that we are going to
find a way to share a frame or else you
know then we won't exchange so at some
level we have some notion that we will
come together and have some reciprocity
or else we wouldn't be connected at some
level and at the same time your frame
and perspective and experience is going
to create a variation on your experience
and position that's different than mine
so there's going to be plurality in
relation in plurality of preference and
emphasis and in value hierarchies and
things along those lines okay so so an
integrative pluralism is a dialectic
between pulling together and allowing
for differentiation so that's a that's a
basic principle it's actually by the way
I would consume
a meta modern principle in many ways in
the sense that sort of modernism it at
least said it's sort of a narrow version
of modernism and it's rationalistic
conception of one truth and
post-modernism with its fragmented
pluralism an identity of meta modern
value would be an integrated plural so
that sort of offers a synthesis between
the modern thesis and the postmodern in
businesses so there's a there's sort of
a cultural sensibility that connect
there but really it's like hey I have a
version you have a vision I bet they
overlap so but I also bet they're
different
and let's preciate that so that's the
first thing when I'm offering my vision
I offer the following I say that you
know in terms of the I have some meta
cultural values that I commit you okay
and by medical sure I mean they sixth
end beyond my nationality and they sixth
end beyond my sense of a westerner or
whatever they're basically positioned me
as a human in the cosmos and say all
right this is Easter and those big three
values are dignity
well-being and integrity okay so those
are my big three values and they
represent dignity the idea of
fundamental human dignity is the grounds
the National Decker if you know United
Nations Declaration of Human Rights
I'd also mean it more in an incremental
way that we can have more or less
dignity respect for ourselves or others
and you know what we do because it's
fundamental dignity well-being is the
mission of the organization but
basically I spend a lot of time defining
what that is technically but you know
it's essentially health and happiness
bio psychosocial health and happiness oh
and we want to cultivate that as opposed
to suffering colloquially defined and
integrity really refers to truth and
honesty to being truth and honest so so
really respect health and happiness
truth and honesty those are those are
the meta cultural values that I want to
play by and I invite that then it's like
you know and if you know
I hope folks will play that if folks
don't want to play that it's gonna be
now hard to play you know I was like
yeah you don't you know do I need to
defend myself physically I don't know
okay tend to be pretty broad most people
find those to be yeah no I think that's
I think that's absolutely beautiful yeah
I resonate so strongly I mean in in a
way it's kind of like we could we could
frame as a dignity as in there are
multiple players well-being that's a
directionality and integrity there's a
conduct to how we play the game so that
even and of course there's much more to
be said qualitatively for these notions
but just structurally we've got here
what isn't it necessary to actually play
I love the way you're riffing off those
things that's why actually that's
exactly the design of those things is
that people as an integrated pluralistic
kind of you you take those each of these
poles and you suck up and you move them
around and you can then project onto
them wide a different so for example you
can go good true beautiful so beauty
connects to dignity and the aesthetic
value well-being to goodness and true to
integrity that's just one example okay
you hit on the other was a great example
which I hadn't heard before but I I've
seen lots of people pick up these big
three and then juxtapose them in very
creative ways that resonate with me but
novelty so that's one of the reasons I
like them is that they do that you did
it wonderful I was in the next and it
shows this sort of intuitively that's
like yeah okay actually if we have this
this is a it's not a it's not a
rule-based framing but it's a healthy
principled process meta value frame yeah
so maybe here is a good opportunity to
to talk about what are the kinds of
practices or because it's funny because
we've just taken a little bit of it of
an intellectual approach just for a
moment in terms of understanding the
importance of these we say we say is it
Metsu virtues what did what what is that
Oh meta values but yeah buddies meta
cultural values yes the sort of long
name for him yeah so yeah interesting I
wonder so we say meta cultural values
how did those values show up you know I
could probably say some things about
this but I'm interested in how how do
those values show up in my experience
can I relate to myself in a way that's
as helpful as I can relate
so from this meta cultural level using
these three tools well I certainly I
certainly use them to relate to myself
so I can share with that and then you
can see how that resonance with you so
in fact you'll see on my signature line
I have what is called my ultimate
justification okay so by justification I
mean my propositional guide which is to
be that which enhances dignity and
well-being with integrity so that's the
way I arrange them be that which
enhances dignity and well-being with
integrity it's beautiful so so and what
I'm thinking about enhancing dignity I'm
thinking about the fundamental concept
of respect respect what do I respected
myself and how do I be in a particular
way that you know not in a harsh
judgment way I can talk about it by a
complimentary to this as my approach to
psychological mindfulness called calm ml
which I could talk about which creates a
context an additional psycho technology
layered context I spoke with it some
about with John
but anyway it's it's when do I know
Jordan bution talks about this also you
know intuitively when you respect
yourself and when you don't so I check
myself on that you know and and I have a
sense about what I want to be not in a
harsh critical internalized parent sort
of way but in a healthy ego way well you
know when I look at myself what is that
about
and what do I value in a healthy way
about me and what not so much and how do
I relate to that in a healthy way so and
then there's well-being well-being like
I said is in a simple ways it's I love
Cohn as a phrase for well-being called
happiness with the worthy just to be
happy so the addition of worthiness to
be happy takes out the smiley face
subjective happy few lies is that in 2d
and we're talking con here so we're
talking about you know not like
philosophy you know it's really it's a
pressured review of depth and this also
for me speaks Aristotle's concept a
unites money on the ultimate end good
and our ultimate concern for flourishing
as opposed to profound suffering the
metaphors of hell and heaven on earth
all of the wrapped up in well-being and
as a clinician of course
psychosocial well-being is
professionally trained in really
essentially what my job is is to
encounter people whose psychosocial
well-being is suffering they're trapped
in maladaptive cycles they've had
traumas occur to them they don't know
what to do and the way they're adjusting
to their environment generally
if I can help them therapeutically the
way they're adjusting is creating more
problems as my job is to understand
those maladaptive cycles that they're
trapped in create awareness and
acceptance and then cultivate
active adaptive change that reverses
patterns towards flourishing that's the
the goal a lot easier something done
ultimately the integrity piece you know
is which is really where I actually
spend a hell of a lot of my time early
on as a psychologist trying to figure
out how the hell do you actually be
assigned akhter of psychology with
integrity it turns out that the field of
psychology
pardon my french but i tell this in my
lectures nobody knows what the fuck
psychology is that's what I just heard
in my training I woke up
that reality and so I was like well shit
I'm supposed to be a psychologist but
nobody knows what psychology is that's a
problem a bit like being a human being
yeah well and they actually are code
connected yeah we connected but that
sparked me on my you know actually
scholarly journey as it were the
question is what is psychology and what
I call the problems yeah I I began
reading I believe a chapter in your book
part of the link that you sent me it
might have been an essay you have to
forgive me if I miss quoting something I
know I've got yeah dumped a lot I only
wrote one book I dumped a hell a lot on
psychology today
yes he's eat again but yes the problem
of one of the things I'm an intellectual
if you want to know my intellectual
story it is the case that I had any sort
of integrity truth level it dawned on me
that there's a profound problem in the
science of psychology and yes
interesting problem in election so and I
would love to hear about it I would love
to hear about it but I suppose I just I
just ask you real quick is there you
know I am because we could spend out
just a little bit more time in the
territory that we've outlined hmm-hmm
yeah so hmm okay so this is a bit of
maybe a bit of a link but you know very
much a link after stretch for so you
mentioned happiness with the worthiness
to be happy
and I'm presuming that I mean I mean in
inferring that the assessment of one's
worthiness is to be made with a kind of
discernment that is in an important
sense from a more mature position and a
certain kind of judgment and there is of
course as I've seen you know in your
work potential there is this helpful
friction point here between how it is we
come to judge or discern or hold
ourselves to account hold ourselves to
account for let's say integrity and then
also the reality that well we do fall
off the path a when we do make mistakes
and there's a certain kind of gentleness
to that process but nevertheless a
hardness right and but not in a way that
further traumatizes oneself but that
does hold you to account and it strikes
me that there's a connection between
this dynamic and the feature of the
features of reality that we encounter in
terms of how we meet that the unknown in
terms of how we come to know ourselves
in part due to being presented by things
about ourselves we didn't know and that
is a bit of a link to the problem some
problems with psychology but of course
psychology is we can you know what it is
is an interesting thing but if we say
some sort of discipline or interest area
and coming to understand the nature of
what the human being you can't even say
as behavior because it's like we can
talk about behavior but then there's
also the inner psychic life and then
this is deeper sense of meaning and
what is it all about and so it's a very
difficult thing yeah
maybe there's a it's probably an
interesting personal story there for you
as to how you came to break from
traditional understandings in psychology
at least I mean it seems to me that in
the middle of the 20th century
you've got a pretty like this sort of
the functionalism positivism behaviorism
that had been kind of dominant in both
philosophy of mind philosophy and and
psychology man that stuff to me is just
like whoa guys what like what we're
missing something that happens right at
there you know go to university and
study after a lot of that happen so you
can maybe it's a bit easier to say when
there are people that are kind of
turning around going yeah yeah we kind
of bit of a joke about that one sorry
[Music]
but how do you how do you relate then to
- can we can we say here it's it's
almost like how do we relate to our own
dissonance you know how do we trust
ourselves through our failures yes and
maintain integrity I don't know
yes well first off let's just say
there's a reason that there's a problem
of psychology it's freaking complicated
it's the intersection of a lot of
different you know lines of analytic law
it's an intersection of you have the
deep subjective experience problem
relative just say if you're trying to do
science from a third-person objective
perspective there's that nightmare yeah
deep issues of value problems and
relationship to you know how do we
predetermine what is good we have an
intuitive sense of what it's good we
don't determine that scientifically we
determine that morally and ethically you
don't scientifically determine somebody
is a priori healthy or good we have a
sense of what healthy good is and then
we have variables that are associated
with that but that's a different so so
how you know and so then we're how do we
apply the values and the understand
to ourselves and then wrestle with all
the things they don't like determinism
in freewill and what can we actually
account for and are we just doing
pragmatic stuff or we really I mean it's
a nightmare you know I feel like I cut
through a lot of that confusion and
created coherence in silicon so that's
that was exciting and it turns out not
at the I will simply say just to reflect
to some of your concern there's a
dialectic you know between when we're
dealing with ourselves and I say this as
a therapist okay there's a dialectic
between challenge and support okay
dialectics so you want to be loved and
you want to be challenged by your
coaches and your parents and the people
who love you right and what you want and
you want to do that to yourself in other
words they're the part of you they're
the the individuals who who will move
you and move yourself are the ones that
accept you and love you both for who you
are and challenge you to be what you can
be that's why I try to do myself that's
why I try with my kids and that's what
I'm being related to in some of the best
ways when other people are doing yeah
beautiful beautiful yeah so yeah so
that's that's in terms of the pragmatics
the practical reason that's a distilled
practical recent dialectic that I would
offer there's also then the theoretical
reason I mean that goes into the problem
of psychology and indeed what happened
to me in graduate school as a therapist
I was learning to do therapy in this you
know we can decide how long to go into
this but basically the short story was
is that I was learning that there was a
lot of value in the various perspectives
okay so the updated Neo Freudian
perspective psychodynamic you that hey
that has a lot of interesting value the
shadow people justify and ya for it was
extreme in some ways but man you know he
and then people like Karen Horn I and
modern Freudian theorist you know a lot
of interesting stuff
I was drawn to cognitive therapy and
ideas from Beck and Ellis and stoicism
and how to justify your your position
and interpretation in a way that is it's
emotionally and behaviorally healthy the
humanistic tradition you know I mean all
good therapy for me starts with Carl
Rogers the Carl Rogers capacity for
empathy and authenticity and holding
that relational value that's you know
Carlos didn't call it that but he called
it the organism evaluate process that he
would not judge but create a context of
relational mirroring projects to grow so
I can that's just beautiful
hmm and so you have you know and scare I
mean scare was unbelievably insightful
for a long time I was armwrestling most
was skinner I finally understood what
the hell he was talking about because
this anti mentalism pissed the shit out
of me and I was like you know you're
missing half the goddamn boat and then I
realized his brilliance of what he
actually was seeing from a position I
hadn't seen originally in the night so
anyway the point is is that you know how
would you articulate that that's super
interesting to me how would you how
would you if you don't mind how would
you what is could Skinner someone as
well that I was just like obviously
loads of great research super
interesting stuff but come on my way
right okay so so basically skaters
okay so Skinner is taking a hard and
pure asses of view of science and and
the philosophy of behavior which is
basically they're going to take a
third-person exterior view and my job as
a psychologist is to determine the
contingencies in response to your
responses that change your response rate
okay that's what he was trying to do and
what he does is he gets rid of Watson's
so Watson the first behaviors has this
idea that inside of you are all these
neuro mechanical reflexes they're
somehow going off through Association
that's Watson that's just dumb okay I
hope your podcast oh man never so yeah
please go ahead so that's just you know
that's just trying to create raw
physical reductionism into the nervous
system that's just you all Skinner who
gets rid of that he jettisons all of
that his philosophy and philosophy
behavior by which he defines it as the
function of the operant okay that's a
very complicated concept once you've
been what you really diet the operant is
the thing that the organism is operating
on and the contingencies that that
operation produces I'll say that again
it's the thing that the organism is
operating on and the contingencies of
that operation that it produces okay so
here's the example I give people people
think about skinner in terms of oh you
know you get stickers or you do all this
other stuff
imagine you're writing along here I have
a pen right here but right now long down
here and this and what is going on when
I'm h marking stuff on the page okay I'm
writing and I'm seeing the ink on the
page so the ink is a function my
behavior is a function of that operon
and as soon as that pen runs out of ink
and it stops writing guess what happens
my writing behavior stops okay you can
see that actually the ink is a salient
control external variable okay that
eating back on my behavior alright and
creating that's creating a reinforcing
control on what it is that I'm investing
yes i extent so it says linker a link of
interdependency it's a link of
interdependence ii and and i i'm not
gonna focus on what you're feeling are
but all I'm gonna do is I'm gonna watch
you on a video and I'm gonna see the
Saleen control variables that you try to
produce and then the impact that that
has on the frequencies of behavior that
you emit mm-hmm-hmm which then he does
Skinner should have used this term but
he was so anti mentalistic so this is
what I discovered us called the
behavioral investment theory okay which
basically says that your nervous system
is an investment value system okay an
investment value system alright which
actually connects you were talking with
John for a key about Heidegger's concept
of care the investment value system is
actually this system cares about where
you're going to direct your work effort
I'll say that again it cares about where
you're gonna direct your work effort
okay
and or your entire behavioral system is
basically an energy economic system all
right that is trying to expend energy
based on things like time okay
opportunity costs risks and what you
decide is relevant for the outcomes that
you're working to produce okay so you
have from a cognitive perspective you
have a hierarchical system of relevance
realizers Godlove Jon right that allows
you to detect what are the appropriate
and salient indicators of information
that allow you to solve problems
efficiently and spend work energy to get
the control that you want that's your
cup of view okay so that's
neurocognitive functionalism so that's
what Neurosci burnett ik people at least
now the 4e cognitive people are
realizing that the nervous system is a
neuroscientific system okay that's
embodied and enacting and fundamentally
behavioral it's this neural cognitive
functional system okay so they're
actually becoming behavioral in many
ways they were up here at the symbolic
function level as like AI and 4e brings
you into the perspective of procedural
embody listen to the way John talks it's
not all a proposition is that it's
participatory well actually when you get
into a John Salkin you're actually now
as I told him you're now jumping into a
skin Aryan view from a third-person it's
it's it's mentalistic lee cold but it is
third-person observation Lee Keeney and
it attends to the environmental
contingencies that are the salient
control variables from the third-person
perspective so it's watching what are
the key variables that are enacting and
soliciting in him you're emitting
participatory procedural action it does
make it does make sense I think that's a
really awesome articulation thank you
for connecting those dots to me it's
particularly that all of that
architecture connects through Skinner in
that way it does strike me that there
and and here might take us on in your
intellectual story a little bit perhaps
although I'm not sure and that is
because I I know there
there's more to come I don't think you
yeah it's a long story friend well yeah
we can do we can have another and and so
and so the thing is is that okay maybe
maybe just to throw just to lob a few
balls at you then novelty as experience
subjectively and perhaps as a domain or
potentiality as a domain metaphysically
and also the it's a lot of what I've
been writing about recently not
publishing anywhere just really trying
to make makino articulations after years
of trying to understand this stuff
regarding then regarding or I referred
to as from one level modes of
orientation so how we like the kind of
the essential elements of orientation in
experience itself like um as as a
conscious entity and it struck it has a
little bit to do with this
not quite ly the mapping is not quite
one-to-one but this challenge support
dynamic is helpful to explain a part of
a particular mode but we we encounter
things we don't understand we encounter
others in relation and yeah we're
consistently undergoing this up and down
the stack relevance realization
processes to understand what kind of
signals are relevant for the my own
regulation of my logistics as a
biological entity with some kind of
unconscious sense or maybe conscious
sense of how I connect to others and
survival needs and belonging needs and
how we're all interdependent there's its
relevance realization up and down the
stack and we're responding to each other
like this and then there's well what
does what does attending to
with what building skillfulness in
discernment in this process what does
that look like to what degree is the
being of us alright the subjectivity of
of us involved what degree can we have
agency what is choice like how can we
invoke participate in our choosing use
like the the fund get a sense of what
the fundament of choice is to help
discern how to inform perhaps even a
small way but it's happening the
metacognitive observer perhaps is part
of what you will come out with this with
but that's kind of where I'm interested
in sort of going you know maybe not see
this okay so lots of things there lots
of balls first thing I want to do is I
want to layer the behavioral investment
system okay on a layer it and I want to
layer it because if we don't layer it
will get confused about because they
different different layers operate in
different ways okay so let me Olivia
give me at least three layers okay so
one layer is your you in relationship to
the material environment as a perceiver
okay so now here you are we're not
talking about a relational layer we're
talking about you in the material
environment as an animal entity that's
moving around okay and has given given
rise you've given rise to at this stage
in the game let's say you're we're not
talking about social relations you're a
mammal and you're just navigating the
environment okay you have a you have a
respectable view which means that
consciousness what I actually call mine
to I have in three different minds I use
in terms of defining domains of mental
process my one refers to the basic
neurocognitive functionalist view that
regulates procedural behavior okay and
that's where that's what so this is
before you have anything that would be
an internal experience being you know at
the most basic level you have snails and
jellyfish engaged
you know reflexes withdrawal mechanisms
these are basically the neural cognitive
reflexive loops that are at the
foundation of neural network building
and they're I would consider them the
pre phenomenological no grain here no
there's definitely nothing that would be
an internal experience of being that we
would relate to as our internal
phenomenology okay so no human
phenomenology here and and not even
animal phenomenology you don't really
you know you get an early brain when
phenomenology emerges but we're gonna
say that phenomenology is present so
that we can answer your question okay um
so we could relate to it so what you
what do you have here is you have a
perception mechanism okay
that's trying to map and predict what is
and what's going to be that's
essentially what you're you have an
investment value system has to determine
what is relevant okay and what it is
doing is its determining what it knows
what it relative to what it doesn't know
and by the way your comment about
novelty is really key here because it's
that's actually what's going to give
rise to almost certainly consciousness
experiential consciousness is a layering
of novelty about checking wait a minute
if it's an automatic perceptional key
that fits you just file it away in your
procedural memory you don't pay any
attention to it it's when you're not
sure you need to pull particular working
memory systems together to determine
what it is that actually you're seeing
it's that onboard memory perceptual
system that's connecting to your
episodic memory that allows you to
actually have the phenomenological
experience of being okay almost
certainly that's it's a global there or
the workspace is the technical term for
that but anyway you basically have a
perceptual system that's tracking and
that's referencing against what your
goal state is okay you have an intuitive
Drive goal state you're trying to
approach certain relations with the
environment and avoid other relations
okay so if you're horny you're
approaching sex right if you're afraid
you're approaching getting hurt at some
particular level all right so if you're
in a prey-predator relationship if
you're the prey you're in an avoidance
mode if you're the predator you're an
approach okay so this
prep you to Mook see and then in
relationship to your goal template and
what you're trying to do with approach
you're trying to reduce that discrepancy
okay and that's ultimately emotion is
the desire you get when you energize
toward your goal state okay
so when the cat sees the mouse he's
gaining on it he's gaining that
experience of approach and desire and
pounces the mouse on the other hand it's
like trying to create a distance freeze
jerk you know anything that expands the
distance okay and if as them as the cat
closes from the mouse perspective the
mouse gets all free and then energizes
with avoidance emotion which is fear
fundamentally an escape okay versus
approach and desire so so you what you
have there that's the perception
motivation emotion formula that's basic
to navigating the world as an animal and
and then not what you're doing is you're
the perceptual system is tracking the
objects and relationships that it sees
if it's looking for something or it gets
novelty it creates an attentional shift
that then brings a layering of
information to the relevance realization
to try to frame that and the reason it's
attentional is because this motivational
system hypothetical motivational system
is like okay we have these drives to
approach in these drives to avoid that
energizes you okay so that's the that's
the first layer of the system now if we
jump up a layer okay now you jump up a
layer now you're start talking about
we're not talking about your
relationship with prey and water or the
material world now we're gonna actually
talk about your conspecific relations
meaning these are the these are the
social relations now we're in a group
like that boons okay that have
long-standing social relations that have
to navigate their cooperation and their
competition each other and and how to
care for each other and how to deceive
each other and how to navigate all of
that
and that is where you want to try to
kind of position yourself socially so
virtually all of what we experience a
relationship to our intuitive sense of
self-esteem our self-worth
it's a socio-emotional process I built a
thing called the influence matrix which
actually Maps the internal working
models of self and relationship to other
on things like dominance and Submission
affiliation and hostility autonomy and
dependency and actually all of those are
in the service of us tracking our degree
of social influence and relational value
it's called the black line on the
influence matrix and basically what it
says is what you're trying to look for
is relational value and social influence
okay that's what your that's your
approach and what you're trying to avoid
is diminishment of relational value or
loss of social influence
that's the avoid piece okay but you
didn't start to think about well how do
i how do I hold myself accountable and
Who am I what do I want to be these are
all internal working models intuitively
that are going to guide you and then the
final layer is now we get into a human
layer okay what I call ultimately mine 3
which is self conscious narration and
justification ok mine 3 is when the
system can actually become you know the
I now it's not just me it's I in
relationship to me and I have I have a
self reflective capacity to look back on
myself and start making judgments and
very importantly I have the whole
process by which I justify myself to
other people okay so now other people
who are me accountable in fact that's
what you learn first as a young kid your
parents and your friends and everybody
holds you accountable and says well why
did you this and why didn't you do this
so you'll be punished if you do this so
you say well I did this because I did
this because and I'm a justifier okay as
a social actor on a stage that says oh
you know I'm trying to do my best
alright and and you learn to justify
yourself and then you learn and really
adolescence is the developmental period
in humans where you really actually
formalize this capacity to become a
consistent self reflective observer
because there's what you called the
adolescent identities like oh shit I in
this way but I could be some
being different and you wander around
with that ability of that self-concept
that just walks with you and many
adolescents go neurotic as hell because
it's like their self-concept is like oh
I wish you were so different and why
aren't you're like Becky she's all hot
and popular and you're ugly and neurotic
I hate you and your model blonde you
know they get nasty internalized critic
and it's a really really brutal one many
people but anyway the point of it is is
then you get that second very reflective
view in mind three where you're
justifying entity so if we're going to
stack relevance realization mechanisms
we have to be very clear about where we
are in the mental domains and processes
because they behave differently across
different layers and then they
interrelate
hmm well thank you for that articulation
that some that's very very helpful so
how to so what comes up for me and just
to put like some cards on the table so
to the extent I have a background that's
well identifiable from an institutional
perspective I was quite interested in
philosophy of mind and at least what six
six years ago now when I was doing you
know I'm more of a scholarly study of
different theories and what-have-you I
at the time was was gravitating strongly
towards a variant of sort of Pan
psychism both so but but but really more
process philosophy so rather than
looking to try and make sense of this
difficult dichotomy or between realism
idealism and then of course dualism
making making a third in that case with
existing kind of metaphysical structure
sort of looking at going at it a whole
different way and not looking at it from
a substance perspective rather a process
perspective and and so I am there are
parts of being that are built up that I
bring to this kind of conversation that
are that that do trigger and wish to you
know understand a little more deeply
the the territory the that that would
have us be able to make sort of
assumptions or statements regarding
where consciousness pops up but I just
want to do that as a sort of a sidetrack
because in some sense consciousness is a
if it is an objective phenomenon as well
as it's a subjective phenomenon of
course it's a very tricky for now
absolutely yes so it opens wherever you
are and let's just dialogue yeah but I
but I think there's a really you know a
really fruitful way we could go in here
and that's to sort of ask you for an
understanding of how let's take mine
three which just less for people who
might not be as familiar stuff that's
happening in in consciousness the stuff
we have it right off human language
based self consciousness okay so it's
actually it's Rene de cartes
like I think therefore I am but its
language based and very importantly it's
everything I could report to you that
you have direct access to in other words
it is my narrator okay so so it's it
sounds the same in my head when I say it
out loud
which is very different than my
perspectival consciousness so I just
write the medium makes a big difference
so the fact that it's linguistically
mediated as opposed to prospectively
mediated that's actually that carries
lots of difference not that they're
inside my head they're interrelated of
course but language only comes out my
perspective never comes out that's
encapsulated in my I mean directly it
comes out indirectly but like my
subjectivity is encapsulated in my
perspective that you can never you'll
never have direct access to my you know
direct access to you but you do get
direct access to my mind 3 as long as I
don't filter it so if I if I just do
what my narrators saying that's
unfiltered and that's just us direct
access to my linguistic thoughts as I do
I share them sure yes thank you sorry
for the no
is a new language system but a so I'm
I've no apologies I just want to be
clear about what it is that's all
certainly yes absolutely absolutely yes
that did lock in with my sense of it I
was just loose but um yeah so so that
actually gets right to it then so how
because there is this phenomenon of we
and there is also an aspect to this
discussion that as well we haven't yet
presents that would be worth kind of
just present seeing now not necessarily
just just to just to get throw this into
the mix as well and that's really a
spirituality and that's yes some of the
more mystical experiences available to
us and these deeper sense of connect
connectivity and and meaning associated
and so it's it's it's something is this
participation in a shared we right and
though I can't access you directly
through a kind of relational indirect
process we can participate in something
together love that a love jars
participatory that's exactly what it is
and in many ways I would argue my
behaviors essentially the opposite side
of my of my coin so we're and they're
very yoked in many ways together so yes
absolutely you I often say to people my
wife in many ways knows me better than
me
not that she knows why phenomena lodging
but she knows who I am by virtue of her
observation of me so we can really know
each other very well I want to be clear
about that and we can we can know each
other interest objectively through our
participating dance with each other the
flow that we create is a way of I love
John's Transjakarta Subba Tori knowing
and and I brace that so yes I'm with yes
yes so so it would seem to me then I
don't know if I'm gonna get this quite
right but because I know you're also
interested in talking about psycho
technologies and what psycho tech
technologies might be helpful for today
and
so it's like what kind of practice what
kind of thing can we do or what is there
to be discovered and how can we and
build skillfulness in that helps that
helps us move from its it's like how do
we its continuity between these three
minds in your language hey is it because
it can it for me it seems well it it
triggers against some of the axioms that
I kind of bring to bear if we consider
things to separately and I don't think
you are considering them separately so
I'm interested I'm a unity non dual yeah
so I'm interested in I'm just trying to
figure out the words that really to ask
you how to articulate that the
interconnections the continuity and how
we can transform up and down the stack
brilliant yeah okay so yes I'm I'm a
substance modest if you want to call it
that our nan duelist in that sense
although the world is it's complicated
because there's epistemological and
ontological meanings to sort out one of
the big concepts that I introduced that
I think is not nearly appreciated enough
is called informational interface okay
informational interface is the
translation between information
processing systems and the interface
between them okay if you appreciate like
my system emphasizes Marshall McLuhan
would appreciate this that the medium of
information transfer is key for its
language is different than phenomenology
so that's okay and once you then sort
out the information processing language
communication control systems that's
speaking the particularly anguish you
also then realize a way there's of
course information interface between
information processing language systems
so this is super or parent right now
I mean I am speaking there's sound ways
that are going into this thing they're
being translated they're being shot up
they're being through the internet and
and translated back into the sound ways
that your speakers are producing that's
it an interface where the medium is
being translated and then transmitted
and translated again through different
information processing systems if we
look at our biology our nervous system
the basic thing that all at the input
level of the nervous system is
transduction input sensory mechanisms in
other words what those things haver
whether it's press on a push here or
electromagnetic radiation through your
eye or sound ways those are all the
miracles of the nervous system is that
it translates through transduction
changes in the world physical chemical
press changes informational and shoots
language neuro language into the system
it's a miracle
and then at an embodied level that
creates procedural behavior okay non
conscious at least the way I'm using the
term non conscious procedural behavior
which we see throughout the entire
organism you know it starts with cells
actually cells are sort self-organizing
subjective they don't have phenomenology
in my language but they have
self-organizing awareness and they make
decisions about what they're doing okay
and so they have that capacity and then
you've networked all that together to
create physiology then you in nervous
system that unifies that and you get
simple animal behavior and then you get
brains that coordinate that they get
brains that create subjective
consciousness or mind - in my language
but all of that is network and it's
network through information information
information interface across different
language systems and it is that
information interface that allows us to
metaphysically account for a lot of the
causal confusions that I think people
get into in terms of like well how does
mine 3 cause anything to happen isn't it
all just physics no it's not all
physics at least in it I mean it's all
physical at when broaden almost
meaningless sense of the word but it's
it's just a faggot ory informational I
mean this entire conversation my mind is
like locked up with yours my mind three
has created a highway of information and
and we have downloaded each other's
informational systems in our and our
phenomenologically move and
physiologically moved as a function of
that is blatantly obvious why the hell
we on the conversation yeah yeah well
that's all that's all that all makes a
lot of sense to me so so if we take if
we take mind one then this um this
perceiver of world this this responsible
for this based participatory relevance
realization in introns language is that
an appropriate mapping just to use yes
although I want to be clear so really
mind one the best way to understand mine
one is what cognitive neuro pathologists
do an ethologist is a science of animal
behavior okay that's ethology or used to
be called comparative psychology and in
psychology gave animal behavior over to
biology which in my system was a trauma
a tragedy
okay so animal behavior should be basic
psychology but now it's biology
but anyway so so the question is how do
you understand what animals do from a
scientific perspective okay that's the
first question and my one really is the
answer to that question so so at a
simple level they have a nervous system
okay so all complex animal behavior is
mediated through the nervous system in
general and brain in particular we know
that typically okay as for what is the
nervous system well it's this messaging
information processing system that
functions neuroscience people call it
the organ of behavior which basically
basically means this takes the behavior
of animals a hole and moves it around
so that's your neuroscience
contributions then you have your
computational cybernetic cognitive folks
okay who study the nervous system as
surely an information processing
computational and cybernetic
hierarchically control system okay so
that's that's what's the cognitive
neuroscience or computational
neuroscience people do then what you
have is you have the behaviorist who
take animals and put them in the lab and
create artificial contingencies either
through association or social networking
or or reinforcement and then they see
how their behavior changes and they have
their language of behavioral science
which tells you how the language changes
based on Association contingency usually
and of course it more advanced now but
that's the early language and it still
builds off of all bullshit okay and then
you have ethology most famously like if
you know somebody like eel Wilson who
was the socio biologist but he was
really an apologist in the sense he
studied ants and social behavior inhales
the early folks were comparative
psychologists but anyway why do animals
do what they do in the world how do you
understand this I just interesting study
on bees bees have crossed mental
modalities where they can recognize an
hour an hour an object through smell and
through touch simultaneous you know they
recognize the same object through sight
sight or smell I think it was maybe it
was touching sight anyway it doesn't
matter they had cross modality
recognition of an item a be a bumblebee
that's what can interesting right he
knows which is whether it smells it or
whether I just said it knows that object
they can that's how they you know that's
the experiment on it's called cognitive
ethology which is you know bringing
cognitive models to demonstrate what
animals are proceeding so so once you
see that what the unified theory says is
actually all of that the meta
theoretical frame is behavioral
investment theory okay behavioral
investment theory allows us to
scientists to understand animal neuro
mental behavior patterns that's the so
it creates a theory that emerges out of
biology is organizes neuroscience and
then organizes neuroscience
this cybernetic behavioral system okay
and then that's called behavioral vespa
theory and that's my one and my one
makes no assertion a priori about the
existence of mind
- meaning that it doesn't tell you when
animals get phenomenological conscious
awareness okay and the reason is because
mine too
is where we get into so many different
philosophical conundrums alright I often
say they're at least two separate hard
problems of consciousness defined in
terms of what my my meaning of mine -
okay so one of them is the
epistemological gap problem the
epistemological gap problem is you never
get to see another entity's mind -
directly that's the nature of it
epistemological II I can never see
another entity's witnessing capacity I
mean that was Thomas Nagel what does it
like to be a bat you know he reviews
that you assume bats have some
respectable experience witnessing
function but what the hell is it like
and how would you know you know that's
the epistemological yeah
okay and then the other serious problem
scientifically is the ontological
problem which is what exactly are the
brain mechanisms involved in generating
the felt experienced witnessing function
okay that's unbelievably that's a that's
a brutally hard problem as far as I'm
concerned that says it's the ontological
problem of mind when we box in a lot of
correlational stuff of what the brain
does but it's still there's huge amounts
of debate and rightfully so the
combination of the ontological and
epistemological problems of my to or are
really you know I can box
I believe I box it in with the unified
framework but I don't answer that those
things remained big time scientific
mysteries as far as I'm concerned as
we're honing in on them I I consider
them scientific mysteries so almost stop
or settle off there at all ya know
beautiful so
oh let me see so you know in the
remaining time we have together which
I'm I'm taking to be maybe thirty
minutes if I can keep you interested
enough yeah oh yes I was kids saw that
you went two hours with John I said I'll
go through hours yeah yeah well it's
it's very interesting just as an aside
point for people listening and my
experience of group conversation and
dialogues in general the one to two hour
mark is is when certain things really
begin to pick up a lot of this is just a
product of time a like if we really did
sit down for ten hours together and go
alright that's all where would we go is
an interesting question
okay we have to go for food at some
point yeah right yeah yeah exactly we
could continue to talk so okay so to
draw to look out in again to the world
and the moment we find ourselves in now
one that threatens fractionation to a
point of destabilization which may
engender certain kinds of collapse
dynamics that seems to be a reasonable
thing to say about a potential there's
other potentials and to stick with some
of the themes of this conversation we've
spoken about the importance of mindset
the kind of values enabling of
relational dynamics that are enabling of
growth or at least we haven't obviously
talent exhaustively
what we see around us in the world from
abroad ecology perspective as well is
mass extinction events we see change all
around us as is always the case of
course is change and of course the cycle
of living and dying is always the case -
but there seems to be again from a
certain perspective a sense that somehow
and we can actually speak to it quite we
can speak to it quite under ectly from
certain game theoretic perspective this
is not that vague actually how some of
the perspectives we can take to
characterize our out-of-touch nurse with
vital relationality on a broad
ecological sphere and we might say it
would be a good thing to come back into
closer touch with what it is to live
sustainably in a growth 'fl way one that
did not render us so fragile to the
collapse of not only all that we care
about but all that we can apprehend or
much of what we can apprehend in nature
as beautiful so and we also have in this
conversation as well gotten into some of
the challenges of speaking about well
you mentioned this a histological gap of
how can we know other minds in a certain
sense and an ontological gap in terms of
understanding what the the like getting
a tight mapping of what the relationship
is between where the brain circuitry or
what is the substrate or how does
phenomenological experience really
really map on to do something we could
look at from say more of an objective
kind of perspective like we can relate
to it in that way but it's like so these
are these are big things to to open into
I appreciate that and I have some other
pieces I have some other pieces to add
because
because there is and I'm also willing to
certainly for the sake of the
conversation but like to to to give up
like this a semantic attachment to
phenomenology needing to be present in
the base of things but you did mention
that there's some kind of awareness or
discrimination you know we can I'm we're
all the processes sense-making you know
I I have where my model led me and and I
and I will say that yes that to the
extent that what I mean is consciousness
to I think it exists hydrogen atom you
know not exactly but whatever in
relationship to there is an interior
perspective I mean live knits talked
about the Monad and they're all just
mystery you know and what white has
brilliant I love process philosophy I
mean I'm yeah applause I get you I think
the I I do think the language is often
and it's so important and it can also be
such an unhelpful barrier to really
doing the but it is a language game I
love thinking Stein's language okay
here's the language let's see if you
could speak it you know so so so so
being so being gentle with this language
then I'm I'm in some respects the the
hard problem of consciousness or at
least the ontological problem it gets
close to where in and this epistle
almost if I can try and bring the
epistemology epistemological problem and
the ontological problem together and
perhaps also with a certain kind of
ethics I want to actually take ethics
with that as well at least a certain
kind of meta ethics and I think that's
what the process philosophy perspectives
ultimately is to be held accountable
right so and and you mentioned something
to do with this in the in the mind one
system of the the
approach that the predator-prey behavior
the approach and the running away right
and in my language I say confrontation
and surrender it could be other other
terms kind of using there's two
different kinds of computation
confrontation two different kinds of
surrender looking to and and and I don't
have things like articulated to
appointment yet where I'm ready to just
go okay here is the kind of the model or
the system but this dynamic of of
of because it being in a kind of right
relationship to what is appropriate
confrontation or appropriate approach
and when should you accept ingression or
when should you reject ingression which
is you hold boundaries and because I
want to link this up with how it is to
come into relationality with each other
and also the issues with our world hey
and it's also this nation this notion of
truth and integrity that you mentioned I
like those values you mentioned Gregg
truly are beautiful hey like what is
this is this is so wonderful dignity
well-being and integrity as you
articulate it and it's like how would
those kind of values serve us as a
mapping at this fundamental mind one
kind of level because if you take the
dignity it's kind of an it it's kind of
an acknowledgment that there is it there
is a dynamic that I'm in relationship to
that I have to take seriously right now
the well-being of course okay there's
something phenomenological about that
from our perspective but in a sense from
you know a base level it's kind of like
well maybe it is I just wish to kind of
survive or this is appropriate for the
continuation of me or what have you but
we have to take that so seriously
because of course if we are out of touch
if we are out of touch and we're
thinking well how is it we came to be so
out of touch but it turns out that
something like that kind of rivalry
towards that in a victory sense is that
fundamental it's like how do we get to
that so the continuity between these
levels so I want to try and preserve
some of this language and I think that
agentic like the choice I'm not talking
about in some phenomenological beautiful
lights archetypal patterns I'm walking
into a forest I'm talking like how to
develop skillfulness in attention such
that with with
with subtlety and gentleness but
nevertheless like a kind of grounded yes
to discern one way or another and have
that mean something hey I mean that's
first off let's just honor that that was
it to me at least that resonates that
was brilliantly articulated in terms of
the dilemmas and the challenges and and
you know the problems and often you know
you want to know the right way to frame
a problem is really key and I just
passionately offered a a really
interesting way to frame the problem so
I just want to sit it up for a second
okay thank you
because that's like yes how do we
actually fucking do this
there's sort of like there's this meta
you know for me it's sort of like I have
this meta schematic right that actually
saw my opinion solve some serious
long-standing fucking problems okay and
then that's very different than actually
well what do you actually do you know
okay and then hi and how do you do it
and and and you know I I really have
deep appreciation for people like dan
I've smoked a murderer and Jordan Paul
and John for baking here's the way I let
me speak for just a second about what I
see where we are okay because I actually
see us I actually think this is a really
important time in this sounds magical
and this where it gets in my spiritual I
actually think of us as an important
time in the cosmos okay from at least a
human are human anthropomorphic here's
the way the tree of knowledge grounds me
analytically in that and then causes me
to be spiritual about that okay which
we'll get back to I don't have an answer
for what you said other than to say
that's the participatory journey of life
and that we all need to sort of figure
out how to dance around so that we know
when to confront and leverage and wake
people up and say what the fuck are we
doing within a degree of assertion and
clarity and quasi aggression that
asserts power and leverages chain
right and at the same time does it turn
in some authoritarian nightmare or end
up getting us crushed by whatever
reaction via listen okay
so this is this dynamic of like okay
well uh and at the same time I don't
know this is what I was gonna say so
come to key points that I want to make
and then come back to why I just would
embrace your participatory not knowing
so at the at the Jordan all John Burbank
II whatever or do sack Stein he says it
nicely we're at a time between worlds
okay
and the future to borrow from Stewart
Kaufman he wrote a recent book on life
and the evolution of complex adaptive
systems it's unprecedented we don't know
we don't know I think 2050 mm - you know
2100 I mean you know all bets are off
and what do we need to look like to have
a sustainable world with how many
billion people I mean are we talking do
five billion of us need to die are we
gonna get up to 15 billion how do we
what skin the plan is sustained anybody
tells you note that they know what that
is ridiculous cuz we don't know what the
technology is lifestyles would be so so
the edge we are on the edge of
uncertainty and the nature of what the
future is is unprecedented
[Music]
how do you know what the right move is
if those are the parameters okay you
don't all right so that's that's the the
Cedars of futuristic Cedars are getting
this right as far as I'm concerned is
like you sit with the liminal that the
liminal is the mystery where we are and
the and you better recognize that we're
on the edge or something that we don't
know if the future is so our task is to
link together the best sense and meaning
making systems so that we can at least
see where we are and where we've been
and at least have the parameters for
where we want to go even as we know we
have no idea how to get there because of
the unknown future lands is the
landscape before us or you know we're a
collective hero's journey
basically we're all in the process of
building ideally building something that
we don't know what it is all has to be
and actually the Tree of Knowledge
teaches us that okay so the Tree of
Knowledge we haven't talked explicitly
about that you I'm sure you come that's
not that's the that's the tree theory of
knowledge and the first branch on the
thing behind me is the tree of knowledge
system okay it's my crazy language
system which I apologize for there it is
the first branch on there is the tree of
knowledge system the tree of knowledge
system says that the universe of is a
unfolding wave of behavioral complexity
that's a universe of unfolding wave
behavioral complexity and first you get
the wave of matter which is just the
material dimension of complicated
behavioral systems okay which starts
simple and then it grows an increasingly
complicated complicated and then on
planet earth and god only knows where
else in the universe a series of
feedback loops happen which I won't get
into that spark life which then gives
rise to this new kind of behavioral
pattern okay that has its own
information processing computational
control regulatory dynamic autopoietic
system of processing so cells behave
very differently than molecules and the
reason is in part is because of the DNA
RNA information processing communication
system that happens within a cell and in
between cells that create the network of
cellular activity that we call life
right well you follow that for a billion
or a couple of two billion years and
certainly then you get to the five
hundred fifty million years ago what's
called the Cambrian explosion okay and a
lot of things happen in between but with
the Cambrian explosion you get the
emergence of complex animal bodies with
brains and a little bit before them but
that's really when it explodes and takes
off and what you get there is a neuro
computational system that's yoking cells
together so that animals behave this
whole unit since the new information
processing system
and a new computational control and
communication system and that's what the
tree of knowledge calls mind which is a
word like life it's just what you see
animals doing in the language system as
I go my dog just walked by those mine a
fish over there in a tank the behavior
of the fish is mental behavior okay just
like you would see a plan call it alive
living behavior okay and then finally
hundred thousand years ago plus or minus
and certainly by fifty thousand years
ago you have what we're doing right now
that's language that is yoking
subjective minds together on a highway
of information building systems of
justification okay that coordinate
people first but the hunter-gatherer
level and then at the horticultural
level and then at the agricultural level
then if the civilization level and then
the hill and there's writing and they
build all these formal systems and
ultimately you get philosophy in science
mathematics okay you get the systems of
justification alright so if you use the
tree of knowledge and you say alright
seriously what has given rise to each of
these qualitative jumps following matt
life mine culture life DNA RNA
information processing coordinated
system together networked mind and neuro
information system language symbolic
communication and language justification
so then the question is well what you
get is what you if there's a novel
information processing system that gets
yoked together and then communicates
amongst itself then you would get
another chunk
so once you see that it's an information
processing system that's yoked together
in an Internet at interconnected network
okay that creates information interface
and artificial symbiotic human
intelligence systems
well shit that's exactly what happened
in the 20th century they laid the
groundwork for all of that and all of
that's gonna get yoked together in the
21st century and that's the digital
landscape so the digital landscape okay
what this conversation is taking place
which collapses across space and time
and allows our justification systems to
be yoked together in a radically
different way that of course 20,000
years ago is just even just pure magic
right if we have this kind of inner
network connection and we have
artificial intelligence big data
communication and then we internet the
Internet of Things connects all of our
machines together then we start putting
shit in our heads right you know then
well welcome exactly welcome to evolve
our Arika you know homo doiis do so
whatever you could have but it's like a
hello right we are actually sitting the
Kyros of this moment not only is like
what's the global institutional
infrastructure but it's also this global
technological boom that creates an
information processing communication
network system that is radically
different than anything we did before
it makes them it makes the printing
press you know look miniscule relative
to what we're so for mm-hm
so this is what's called the on the tree
of knowledge each one of these jumps is
a joint point so you go from energy pure
energy of the Big Bang to matter that's
joint point one matter to life that's
joint point to life to mine that's
showing point three mind a culture is
joint point four
this is joint point five that the 21st
century is about and it's unbelievable
every one of these joint points is
really key and they're complicated and
they're vulnerable because you're on the
educate and the dynamics then between
order and chaos you're gonna get all
waxed and I really think that we are
actually at that point and there's a
miracle of a thing called the
singularity I don't know if you've been
you know tracking this at all but
there's a thing you know called the
singularity Ray Kurzweil popularized but
there's actually a tracking of the
evolution of complexity and I can
explain what I think this means but
ultimately acrosses as a mathematician a
Russian mathematician that nailed this
down from 20 27 to 20 29 who crossed the
threshold of the singularity okay
fascinating unbelievable actually
imaginable as far as a mystical I don't
know if you're familiar with a Roy
Bhaskar and his later years he developed
what's called meta reality he was a
grounded philosopher and then actually
popped into this real spiritual view of
the universe which which is why I have
deep respect for pan psychic views and I
don't know he'll who the hell knows is I
mean maybe the baby God is calling us to
wake up you know I mean you know I'm
agnostic about that but I have seen shit
and I have my theory connects me to shit
that I can't even possibly fathom so I
that awakens me to a spiritual notion
I'm Abed I'm agnostic about but that is
a calling it's an ultimate concern it's
it's a way in which I place the purpose
of my life yeah so yeah so that's my
frame and then you come back to well
what you do with that well Tim
articulated that dilemmas about what
they actually do brilliantly I don't
know it's my architecture what do we
actually do well each of us are journey
so look yeah it will thank you for that
that was a beautiful articulation I mean
I have some ideas about what to do you
know and it seems to be developed
cultivate skillfulness or worthiness
maybe to extend invitations
to engage in a certain kind of movement
of understanding yeah there seem to be
it does seem like there are important
questions that must be transformed and
that a certain sort of participation in
with each other in the transformation of
those questions is an appropriate
grounding or aspiration and in that aim
now that of course itself is is not
giving a definitive answer but it's
opening to a kind of process perhaps
better enabling of coming to terms and
maybe coming to a certain sort of
acceptance with who we are in the nature
of who we are and there are some other
things there are some other things to
say too I mean the I've noticed that in
the at the closure of many good
conversations comes an opportunity to
extend an invitation for another
conversation which is something I would
love to do and if not with you you and I
with some other people as well so see
how to do this kind of thing with with
multiple people as is happening in a few
different places right now but if you're
interested I would love to talk to you
again in that kind of way yeah yeah yeah
I'm just having us here I lead a society
called theory of knowledge Society and
on on Monday we you know we were just we
just yesterday days all blend together
yeah you know we had a group of almost
20 of us for almost two hours
the thought topic was mindfulness okay
and what that was and what it wasn't the
unified framework offers an integrative
approach
to psychological mindfulness that's
capsule in the acronym calm Emma and it
provides I talked to Sean for Becky a
little bit about that provides my sort
of opening frame for psycho technologies
that would enable processes that would
be conducive to the dialo goes element
and those kinds of elements so I love it
by the way I have I have read into a
little bit I appreciated it in that
conversation if you if you if you
wouldn't mind giving like I know it's a
bit ridiculous to give like a one-minute
or two-minute sort of it's actually it's
designed actually it is designed to be
very quick okay so first off I'll say
it's approach to psychological
mindfulness that's a little different
than meditative mindfulness but at the
word mindfulness that means you want to
cultivate awareness and acceptance
virtually the thing that mindfulness
always as opposed to rejection and blind
mindlessness
that's so mindfulness means you want to
cultivate awareness and a position of
acceptance psychological mindfulness
that it means that I'm going to come at
it from a more analytic perspective
rather than meditative mindfulness which
would be able witnessing mine too
subjective phenomenological when you
meditate you train yourself to attend to
your witnessing function the comment oh
is train yourself really how to adopt a
more like an internal therapists view
okay so that's not surprising given my
training all right so really quickly mo
stands for a metacognitive observer okay
which basically means you step outside
the stream of your action and take an
observer view from a meta perspective
okay it also doubles as the term mo
which is modus operandi and when I say
that I say that what I'm going to teach
you is simple
at one level but very hard to do okay
and then the analogy I often use is like
well if I told you that basketball is
about taking a ball and flipping in a
hoop that might sound kind of easy but I
could talk to you for three minutes
about basketball
you have no idea okay
I say that in terms of you know I can
give you a frame but actually six
practice and so really it's a
psychological skill set so metacognitive
observer and modus operandi they
cultivate okay and that's a that's a
perspective that on yourself and on
others that is a participant observer
and then calm so the first thing you do
is you say the word and you invite your
body to be calm okay and then you're
gonna invite your mind and ultimately
your spirit which is your ultimate
concern to be calm and we can call that
from John 4:18 we call it a vertical
move since that I want to get into my
body into my effect into my higher
cognition ultimately my spiritual
concern and kama courses you know
position then against the anxious
defensive threatened view and if you
know things about like polyvagal nerve
there you'll know that basically what
I'm trying to do is try to get that open
system of participation okay so calm
body calm minecon spirits first thing
then the second thing is that calm
stands for an acronym okay it's an
acronym it's not just the word it's an
acronym that cultivates the attitude
that we're trying to in a an act an
engender
of intra psychically and interpersonal
and whether the C stands for curiosity
so now I want to create a mindset of
curiosity and openness as opposed to
closeness and criticality and I should
say by the way the originator of an
element of this was Dan Siegel he's an
interpersonal neurobiology so I really
like and he had coal and I'm bringing it
in but I'd like to make sure he gets
credit anyway so curiosity the second
word is as for acceptance and this is
what the Buddha taught us in terms of
really the capacity to be and be present
okay to detach from your emotions in
terms of I need to feel this way know
you are feeling this way and you have
the capacity for radical acceptance be
acceptance of self acceptance of past
acceptance of the way the world is
acceptance of other not in a do whatever
you want sir away but just a capacity to
not resist okay
suffering in Buddhism is a combination
of pain and then resistance acceptance
is the inverse of resistance
psychologically we often talk about is
to stress tolerance and service skills
from the way so acceptance acceptance of
feelings acceptance past expectance of
self acceptance of other the L stands
for loving compassion loving compassion
is the fundamental attitude we gets back
to dignity where every individual has
dignity we want to cultivate that in my
self compassion cultivates the idea that
I hope for wellbeing for you and your
loved ones I hope for wellbeing for
myself okay I wish I don't want to
bestow suffering upon anybody as a
fundamental compassion in that too
and finally motivated refers to
motivated toward valued States B in the
short and long term so I need to know
what my valued states of being are
that's what I aspire to notice this will
create a dialectic between being and
becoming okay which Orient's my value
state and it Orient's an in relationship
to what do I want out of the here and
now and short term and then what am i
position a week three months three years
through the end of my life and my eulogy
value says you know people so how do I
organize my long term valleys so I want
to position myself that's what my
coaches my internal guide this is what
it's providing me but the support and
encouragement and the challenge to be
and that's what the calm mo mindset is
about and and the argument fundamental
is we create a culture of that
individuals extend calm mo to ourselves
and others and you do the same to me
that's creates a very very different
ecology on talk about ecology of
practices it's an ecology it's a
relational and intrapsychic ecology that
enables you really what it's fundamental
of course how do you deal with conflict
how do you deal with you know intense
disagreement how do you deal with your
own neurotic tendencies well calm mo
actually serves as a balm you know calm
balm in British so the maladaptive
processes that are so often engender get
actually are brought to bear and then
they're reversed and this is what my
training as a psychotherapist really
taught me it's like it cut encapsulates
all the processes and principles that we
identify and reverse maladaptive cycles
inter psychically near personally and
then it creates the kind of fertile
context so that we can grow adaptive
relational and inter psychic modes
beautiful thank you so much for that I
think it's um a very smart and elegant
inclusion of so many important things
that I am yeah I'm in no doubt of their
of their help if we can if we can enter
into this disposition yeah I know we're
just my friend who's a sociologist I
taught him this calm mo he as a good
gesture he's a professor but as a good
gesture on weekends trying to help
people um he has a truck and he started
renting it out to people in need to help
them move okay so he was telling her
fruit that he had learned calm mo last
year-and-a-half from me because he's a
friend of mine and he really
internalized it but he learned it as a
sociologist he don't really understand
sort of the depth of clinical
functioning but he's taught himself he's
taught it to his kids and he's any you
know so he gets up to somebody and he's
working with you know because he's doing
this basically as a charity he's working
with some really brutalized people okay
so he rides up and he's you know for 10
bucks he's moving and I spend in half
his day for ten dollars basically Jerry
got something he's like this truck sucks
you know what did you break this truck
for I thought you had a decent truck so
so Joe was basically like hey in his old
days he would have said fuck you you
know yeah being kind and you're being an
asshole and I'm driving off so that
activated and then he would have
ruminated about it and would have been
all pissed
I know so instead what he did is he
immediately triggered calming himself
and was like huh okay yes I see the mist
that makes sense what do I really want
to do and then he was like well I wonder
why this guy is pissed
no well shit if I were moving and I was
stressed and I was moving into a crack
house from a crack house I'd probably be
pretty pissed off too right you be and
so he actually did an emotional jujitsu
and basically say hey I see it's not the
kind of drug you want to try it anyway
you know it's probably better than
nothing but it's totally up to you dude
so in other words he basically just
absorbed the hit and then decided I'll
give you you know an olive branch even
so and like very quickly the guy then
went from hot to neutral and over the
course of the day went from very
appreciative and then banked a guy and
it worked out fine yeah
and so that's just an everyday example
of somebody who you know not a
psychologist but just learning to flip
the calm switch quickly when he got
bumped by you know an aggressive and
totally unfair you know kind of attack
and reminded me of your comment cuz like
well maybe you should write and then
welcome to our dilemma you know when
when we expend the olive branch how when
do we not get taken advantage of I mean
what if the guys I mean these are all
you know that's why I see great
questions I don't know the answers to
but there are principles and processes
that might enable us to increase the
likelihood yeah well this is a beautiful
place then to sort of give a nod to a
conversation we might have in the future
certainly there's more to be said if we
were talking for 10 hours I do think
there are some other places we could go
so I'm excited about that and I would
just leave you with one parting image if
I might because it just kept recurring
to me over the last 20 minutes of you of
you speaking and sort of a a gesture
towards that the unknown Ness of our
moment and the nature of all of this and
it's what was coming to me was
the process of the breath hey and this
notion of well if we were to just if our
experience of duration was so radically
changed maybe from the perspective of a
fly you know just you know without being
too technical you move in your hand you
know and that fly sees it like it's just
the slowest thing in the world just
lazily moves out the way it's like the
universe or our moment or civilization
as a breath and so far we've just been
drawing in and we think we can keep
drawing in or breathing out forever but
the breath only makes sense given the
relationship between both expansion and
contraction and at that moment of the
shift and so it's making sense from both
sides hey it's like the the desire to
breathe in but then also that only makes
sense if there is also this
countervailing movement of moving but
moving the other way and so that
dialogical relationship then between
expansion and contraction and the nod to
the continuity of all of this and so
much more to come yeah I'm just very
grateful very grateful for your time and
therefore for reaching out and and for
us having this conversation I really
look forward to some more me too that
looks beautiful Tim actually touch me I
love that dialectical image of the
breathing in and breathing there that's
a beautiful song if you would like to be
part of dialogues like this group
conversations then you can follow the
link to the website in the description
this really is a call to participate and
hey let's see what we can do